[Music]
Welcome Mental Health Monday family. So
good to see you guys here. We apologize
for our delay. Um we were having some
technical issues. I'm tired of saying
that to be honest. And this time it was
like we got a new system so we wouldn't
have those problems and then um we're
still learning the system. So there was
a simple thing to do and we figured it
out at the at the last minute. We were
about to not go live but praise God we
are here live. Um and I see that we have
just a couple of faithfuls who who hung
on. Hopefully uh the others will uh
check back or some were tuning in late.
I see it's creeping up just a bit. So,
uh, we are thankful that you are here.
We have an important topic and of course
we are not going to get to all of it
this evening because we are having an
abbreviated um program because we're
starting late but we will continue to do
the program not next week but the week
after. So we will um since we produce
and host our own program we can we can
cover as much as we want and take as
long as we want. So however long it
takes. This is a very important topic,
but I want to say welcome to my co-host,
Dr. Ricardo White. Thank you so much.
Happy belated birthday and welcome back
from Hawaii, it sounds like. Thank you.
Yes, that's our favorite little getaway
spot that we can sneak away to sometimes
just to get uh refreshed. You know how
the Bible says you need to go rest a
while, go take some time away. That was
our time away. and it definitely was a
good um uh refreshing um to me and my
husband. So, thank you for the birthday
greeting, too. It was nice to spend my
birthday there as well. So, yes. Okay.
Well, we have, of course, Clint, one of
the faithful, hung on, Clint, you knew
we were we were coming, Clint, we were
coming. So, it's good to see you here.
Uh Lynette Buffong Buffong. Okay. Good
evening to you. Uh, nice to see you
here. Uh, Muse Black, you were the first
one. And I don't know where you're
watching from, Muse. Um, but it's good
to see you here. Please put in the chat
where you're viewing from. Robert Green,
good to see you.
I suspect was probably first, but then
jumped off. Yeah. Yeah, probably. He was
like, "All right, they'll be He probably
kept checking to see. I'll keep checking
if they get on." So, thank you.
technical difficulties going through
this but just on the content because
it's really really important. It is very
important content. Very important
content. Whenever you and pastor Myers
are presenting, he talks about this
principle of repeat and enlarge. That's
right. So that's what we're going to do
tonight. We're gonna got to repeat it.
Okay. Yes. No, that's will
enlarge. I want to give you this
overview. The reason it's so important
is it's because it's almost like alcohol
is the silent killer. It's been around
so long. We started we hear about the
opioid crisis, but we now are losing
sight that wait a second alcohol is
still doing some serious damage, right?
And you hear about fentinol all the time
and all these type of of drugs. Yeah,
you're right. You're absolutely right.
And we're going to jump into that. Just
welcome everyone uh who is here. Want to
say hi to Ashley Owens. Thank you for
the birthday greeting. And yeah, it's
great to see all of you. Absolutely. And
you know what? You guys can please share
on your social media uh what you're
watching. Invite people to come and join
you because this is a topic for
everyone. This is a topic for everyone.
Um because as Dr. White was saying, it's
like the silent killer that nobody is
talking about. Um, and when we get into
it, I'll I'll give my some of my
perspective on why that is. Um, but we
want to take a deep dive into um the
addiction of alcohol and also look at
what it does to the person obviously and
looking into all of that, but also what
it does to relationships and to um to
those that they love, how how that
affects them. And I'm sure many of you
have been on some level affected by, you
know, either a close family member or
through a friend who may have had an
alcoholic parent or or um or a loved one
um and they were very impacted by that.
So, we're going to take a deep dive into
that. So, give us the numbers, Dr.
White. What is alcohol doing? How many
lives uh does alcohol addiction take per
year? So it's on average, but I remember
when I was in training the number was
80,000.
As if that's not enough, right?
Currently the statistic is 140,000
people dying annually in the US from
alcohol related causes. Just for
context, imagine 380 people dying daily.
Okay. Wow. That's about a death every
3.8 eight minutes. All right. 44% of
those dying are dying from chronic
conditions like liver disease, cancer,
high blood pressure. But 66% are dying
from acute issues like alcohol
poisoning, car accidents, falls,
homicides, and suicides. One of the
really concerning things of Ponte is
there are people who can start a binging
episode not suicidal.
Not suicidal. And in the midst of that
drinking episode actually commit suicide
under the influence of alcohol. So it it
really is a silent killer because it's
one thing that you are already feeling
suicidal. It's another that you were at
your psychic
baseline and now because of
intoxication now you that that's really
really um tragic but 140,000 people
dying annually. So that is tragic. Yeah.
So that is tragic. something else. And I
I like what I'm I don't like what Clint
said, but I think it's I like it as a
comment just to um because I think it's
it a lot of us um have dealt with that.
Um but it says, "I grew up in a
household where alcohol was such a
normal band-aid." Wow. And I like how
you put that uh Clint because you to
give it the term a band-aid and that is
what alcohol and really any other drug
is. It is to just cover up those
negative emotions. You don't want to
feel it. So it's we try to numb
ourselves. Um you know that's and so
alcohol will do that. Try to numb
yourself from feeling those negative uh
emotions. But I just like the analogy
that you used calling it a band-aid
because that is how it can start for
some people and then it turns into an
addiction. And so that next question
then would be then, hey, what's the
difference between social drinking
versus when it's an addiction? You do
want to know that there was a
2023 study um that said just one drink
and raise the risk of death. Um so a
massive 23 study published in the JAMAMA
network found no amount of alcohol is
safe. Even moderate drinking is
associated with increased all cause
mortality. risk increase begins um to
appear just one drink per day for women
and two for men and the article in
JAMAMA 2023 Journal of the U Journal of
the Medical
Association. Um,
so that's that's interesting when you
start to see that, you know, even
science is saying no, there's no safe
there's no safe amount,
right? Something to be aware of. And
then of course, alcohol impaired driving
causes one in three traffic. So over
10,000 deaths annually in the US are due
to alcoholrelated crashes. So this is
not something we talk a lot about. The
other thing is you see so many people
adding to their brand alcohol. You see,
and I'm not going to call anybody out,
but this is almost like a right of
conscience. And you see them making a
lot of money. By the way, how much do
you
think America spends on alcohol in a
year?
That an because I couldn't hear you that
well. Did you say an average American or
in America we spend on alcohol in a year
as a whole? You could do either one, but
um I was thinking just how what's the
total amount spent on alcohol in the
United States in one year?
I'm taking I'm just taking a shot in the
dark. So, um a billion dollars I How
much?
383 billion.
383 billion. Wow. I was so off. No. And
when you break Well, the billion is good
because a lot of times people go even
under that. Um, but when you break it
down, that's almost like
$600 for every man, woman, and I forget
if it's child included. Let me see if I
can get you the exact stat, but it's
it's astronomic when you really think
about it. That is so much
money. That is so much money. But that
lets you know how big of an industry it
is. I know we're not talking about
addiction right here, but it's that's
how big of an industry it is. And when
something is that big, they don't want
you. Okay, I don't want to sound like a
conspiracy show here, but they don't
want you to stop. They want you to
drink, right? Or they want you to like
abuse this because it's making so much
money um for someone
and and I think sometimes people just
don't know, but you living mana
audience, we want you to be aware and we
want you to recognize this for the risky
thing that it is. Mhm. So, so first we
just wanted to ground the conversation
so that you can understand no this
really is a very important issue. This
really is an important issue and that's
why we wanted to give you some of those
um statistics.
Um yeah, any anything else that you
wanted to any any questions or any
issues? Yes. Um, and just like you're
asking me questions, but we want you
guys to put your questions in the chat
as well, so that we can that so that we
can talk about it. Um, but just I'm
still just blown away by that number.
Um, but when I think about um
addiction, I mean,
what because alcohol is a substance,
right? It it can change your um your
mind or you know it's it's a substance,
right? So what other substance um
besides I guess cigarettes um nicotine
right that um is promoted the way
alcohol is and I can even say that
nicotine or cigarettes is not even
promoted the way alcohol is. Um maybe it
used to be but not in the last what 30
or 40 years it hasn't been as promoted
as alcohol. I mean, you have commercials
that are promoting alcohol and um you
know, it's just it's like it's promote,
you know, when you turn 21, you can
legally drink. It's okay. Now, it's just
it's it's just something that it's not
looked at as a negative in our society.
It's not negative. Only if you're young
and you're a teenager or whatever, then
it's a negative. Um, and then of course
when people do abuse it, then it's a
negative. But it has to get to that
point before it's a negative for our
society. It's just not portrayed. You
know, you have you have the image of the
strong person and they're attractive and
they're surrounded by, you know, the
opposite sex and there's everything that
you would kind of aspire to be and it's
quietly centered around that drink in
your hand and it just being the ultimate
mark. So, I just want to give you the
the specific statistic. In 2023, the
average annual expenditure per consumer
unit on alcohol beverage was
$637, up from 583 in 2022. So, I just
want to specific statistics. Um, so just
wanting to uh take a deep dive like
um what
happens well addiction period, but what
happens in the brain? um to someone who
um gets addicted to alcohol because you
know people are thinking like well I you
know I drank some I wasn't addicted to
it but then some people do get addicted
so what happens in that to that person
who gets addicted so one of the things
that happens when you drink alcohol is
initially
um you actually relax okay because of
course it'll go to the brain and so
it'll relax and so This is what gets a
lot of people started because when you
go to a social setting, you're kind of
tending like a drink kind of reduce that
anxiety. But unfortunately, it doesn't
stop there. It it can continue until of
course it can progress all the way to
intoxication and even a person getting
comos. I think the interesting thing is
that with repeated use, alcohol goes to
a a place on the on the neuron and what
it'll do is it'll actually decrease the
rate of firing of the neuron. Okay?
And when the body gets habituated, when
it gets accustomed to that, in the
absence of alcohol, there is increased
firing of that neuron.
So in other words, in the absence of
alcohol, the anxiety kind of goes up. It
goes up. Now, if the anxiety is going
up, guess what it's going to encourage
you to do? Drink. Drink more. You're
going to drink more. Drink more. Drink
more.
You can see the cycle.
And so, so a lot of people say, well,
you know, I drink because it relaxes me.
And they sometimes don't even well, I
guess they didn't recognize them, but in
the absence of alcohol, it can progress
to where they are they are having
tremors. They're having tremors. Um, and
they need the alcohol or at least they
use the alcohol to self-medicate the
tremor. So you did say this was going to
be repeat and enlarged. We wanted to
show you this is a really fascinating
discussion and you want to be here when
we continue this discussion um I guess
two weeks from now. Um so I so we we are
going to have to stop at um
5:45 um because of uh because of an
issue that I um at the beginning. Um but
I but we we we wanted to ground you in
understanding even though we don't talk
about alcohol addiction a lot um it it
really is kind of a silent kill. It it
has a profound impact um and it's
something that it's it's wise to avoid.
It's it's wise to avoid according to the
John McFetti. It's like, hey, we can't
anymore say there is that one drink is a
good idea. Um, that is something the
research is not it's just not bearing
out. Right. Clint has a good question.
He says, "How can you help someone who
abuses alcohol? What are some general
methods of approach?"
Okay.
So, uh it's funny because the approach
is going to vary depending on where they
are in their process. Um so, I'm sure
you're familiar with the stages of
change.
And so, um this is in motivational
interviewing. What it highlights is that
people will be at a different point in
their recovery journey.
um from not interested at all in change
to very motivated and very interested in
change. So that each phase of that
requires a different approach. Um and so
that that's what complicates the
discussion. Um Clint, so now obviously
the person is not motivated at
all. Um that's where boundaries are
important. Um, and it's a situation
where it's okay, I have to control what
I can control. I can't control your
behavior, but I've got to control my
behavior. So, right, if you're
intoxicated and I've noticed that you're
unsafe to be around when you're
intoxicated, then I'm going to withdraw
from you um during those. and and you
basically figure
out what are the boundaries you're going
to need to set um in order to keep the
relationship safe.
And now you can see why professional
consultation can be so important um
because it's at that point that you can
you can describe your experience with
alcohol. You can ex you can describe the
goals that you have where this fits so
that you can get some very nuanced
recommendations on what it is you need
to do in order to in order
to optimize the relationship as best as
possible. So that is a great question.
Um, and and I hope that you see
um I hope that you
see why it's important to get the
necessary attention. This stuff is not
just intuitive and it's a mistake to
think, okay, I can just use my best
guess. A lot of our best thinking um is
not going to help the situation. There
are knee-jerk things that we're inclined
to do that'll make it worse and things
that we might not be inclined to do that
might help the situation more than you
would think. Um, what are some of those
things that are knee-jerk um, uh, things
that we might do that might make it
worse? I'm sure many would like to know.
So, they don't they don't do that. So,
for example, there's a condition called
codependence, right? And for example,
it's you know what, I've got the power
to keep you from drinking. All right.
Right. And we are just going to do
everything like it's sort of like the
chain you to the bed kind of mentality,
you know, right? I'm going to jail you
and I'm going to keep tabs on you and
all this kind of like when in fact you
wouldn't believe how creative people are
in that kind of atmosphere.
Um, you know, um, saying that what it
ends up doing is not working. Like
anyone who's taken up that approach and
has
a moderate amount of self-awareness
um will recognize that this is not a
winning strategy. Um I really should get
some professional consultation, but it's
the knee-jerk thing that you're inclined
to do. Okay, I I can I can do for this
person what they actually need to do for
themselves. Um I see that work um very
well. So that's the that's the thing
that I would say. I'm gonna have to
leave it there for now. um you know uh
sadly. Okay. So, you're having that
other call that you must take. Yes.
Absolutely. Got it. Got it. Um I think
we Okay, I will try to take some of your
questions if there's things that I
cannot answer because I'll be like we're
going to ask Dr. White that on our next
session and I will definitely we're
going to table that. But I will, you
know, go into some of the areas that I
feel like I can cover. Um we just have
about 15 more minutes together and so uh
we will we will do that but we are going
to come back in two weeks and have Dr.
White of course back to be able to go
deeper and I unplug a stress
uh mastery webinar that we will be
hosting. Um, so is it stressful or what?
You know, and so, uh, April is actually
stress awareness month. And so, the
Mastermind Institute will actually be
hosting a webinar to teach you a
powerful framework for helping you deal
with stress. And the link um, is going
to be in the in the chat so that you can
register for that. So we can know how
many people we need to prepare for
circulate it as widely as possible and
it's free.
Yes, you guys want to take advantage of
that and it is in the chat. So please um
click on that link um and you can always
go back after this program ends. You can
always go back and um look at it in the
in the um in the chat so that you can
see the link um so that you can be able
uh to get that information and go. It's
free, guys. So, you want to you want to
go. It'll be a blessing. Um, okay. Thank
Yes. Thank you for that. And we'll
mention that. Um, we're only going to be
here for a few more minutes and we'll
mention it again. But thank you, Dr.
White. And we will see you in two weeks.
See you in two weeks. Thank you. So,
yes, again, want to thank everyone for
being here this evening. As you can
tell, it is an abbreviated version of
mental health Monday. And we don't get
our Dr. white with us the entire time
because he had to run off and take care
of um some important things. But I just
wanted to stay on here just for a few
minutes longer, give you guys an
opportunity to
um ask more questions or even comments
um just about alcohol addiction. Um you
know, you know, Dr. White is a
psychiatrist and he specializes in
addiction. So he covers that in an area
that I don't specialize in. But what I
do specialize in is in uh therapy uh for
for for for individuals, for couples and
for families. And so I just wanted to
highlight that you know so many times
you know I have families individuals
that come in and they have so many
issues um as adults that they're dealing
with. Um, and as I get deeper into their
story, you know, it comes to find out
come to find out that they um were
raised by an alcoholic, either their
mother or their father or maybe not even
an alcoholic, but from a parent who
abused drugs. And so that brings um a
host of issues um into uh their life.
Not it didn't just bring it in as
adults, they always had it even as
children. Um but it carries through all
the way through um adulthood and it
really shows up in their relationships.
A lot of times there are
insecurities. Um they just don't feel
safe. Um they a lot of times they have
attachment uh issues. So they have
insecure attachment. So they don't know
how to allow people to get close to them
because there's always fear. Um, when
you're being raised by a parent that was
an alcoholic, you just never know how
they're going to come home. You never
know if this is going to be a good
night. You don't know if, you know, dad
or mom are going to be um abuse abusive
to each other or abusive to you. So,
there's just a lot of just continual
running anxiety um in children. And then
that doesn't stop, like I said, even
into adulthood. And again, it shows up
in their relationships um when they're
trying to have um a normal, happy,
healthy relationship with their um
significant other and they find it very
extremely difficult
uh to do that. Um or even in raising
their children, they um have picked up
some very bad habits from their um their
parent that is addicted to alcohol or
other
substances. Okay, we have a question.
and I feel like I have an addictive
personality. Is that truly a thing? Um,
yes, that that is a thing. And usually
that comes from other emotional issues.
Meaning um it's a thing because you
can learn that you can you can try to
cover up other emotional issues by
always uh being addicted to something or
always being high on something. Like
like I said at the beginning of the
program, being addicted to a substance
that numbs emotions, negative emotions
that you don't want to feel or you don't
want to think about. So because of that
and because you've been could have been
going through that or dealing with that
for so long, it's just easy to be like,
well, I'll just drink or I'll just smoke
it away or I'll just sniff it away or
whatever the choice of um addiction, a
drug or a substance that you're wanting
to use. So hopefully that makes sense.
It's not like you were just born like
you have an addictive personality. No,
it's it's the trauma and things that
have happened to you um throughout your
life that
have pushed you or um just really taken
you in that direction into that space.
So hopefully that that makes sense.
Um I see some other comments on here. Um
it says the book Steps to Christ
Recovery Edition. All right. Okay. Um,
oh, with the 12step program of Alcohol
Anonymous. Okay. Yeah, that's really
good, too. So, yeah, there's definitely
amazing things that there's help.
There's resources out there for um
addiction. And so, um that that sounds
like a very good uh resource. And
there's other there's others as well.
Um, but it is it is something
that, you know, when you go when people
go into rehab, they're dealing with a
lot of the stuff that I'm talking about.
I mean, to be able to really get down to
the foundation of why uh you are finding
being addicted not just to alcohol, but
other substances, um, you're you're
wanting to find out the root of where
this is coming from. What? Why was this
such Why was this an option for you? Why
was did you feel like this was a better
choice? What pain are you trying to
cover up? What what are you trying to
numb yourself from? Um those are the
areas that I know in addiction recovery
that they they deal with. And when
you're in individual um addiction
recovery, definitely want to to go into
those areas. Um just looking for any
other questions or comments. Um let's
see. It says, "I'm aware many new SDAs
give up alcohol but have not dealt with
the trauma of life." I agree. I agree
with that, Gloria. That is so true. Um,
and so they may give up alcohol um
because socially now that they've
they've learned that, you know, socially
because they're in a Christian
uh space and setting that's not okay.
But they can they if they don't deal
with the trauma, they will turn to
something else negative. And it may not
be a substance, but uh but it's still
there. It's still not going to be
something healthy. They you always want
to deal with the root issue. Whatever
that root issue is, that foundational
issue, if you will, that needs to be
dealt with for you to really be healed
from what um was causing you to be
addicted to any substance in the first
place. Let's see. How do you balance
your commitment to your husband when
addiction is involved in trying to raise
your children dealing with the chaos? So
Ashley, um that's definitely a hard one
when um there's, you know, one parent
who um is addicted to a substance and
there's um young children and you said a
balance.
So, and and you know, if there's there's
so many there's so many other I mean
more to a situation like this. I mean,
if the the spouse is not willing to get
help, I definitely would have um my
children and myself in therapy if that
was my situation. um just because we are
both coexisting and living with an
alcoholic spouse spouse and they're
dealing with an alcoholic parent. Um if
you're in danger or if the children are
in danger and there's abuse that's going
on then you have to work with a you know
I would you know you need to I would
tell anyone to work with a mental health
professional um so that you can make a
decision if it's safe to leave or if
that's the best decision to leave if
it's not safe for you or the children.
But if it is a safe, relatively speaking
situation, I would definitely get myself
and my children into therapy because
they're being impacted by being exposed
and being raised by an alcoholic um
parent and so is the spouse.
So that is um that's what I would tell
anyway anyone and I hope if I was in
that situation that's what somebody
would tell me uh because you're needing
uh to get support or to get to get help
in that situation. the children are
definitely going to need it cuz it is
not easy. What happens when children are
raised with alcoholic parents? Um they
always have to walk on eggshells because
they never want to just like trigger the
alcoholic parent. Um so they just always
they never feel like they can really say
how they really feel. um they will just
learn how to just cover it up and then
they take that with them throughout
their life and into their adulthood and
um they don't speak up when they should
and they allow things h that to happen
when they shouldn't and then but then
they have a lot of anger. So there's
just a lot of stuff in there for
children who've been erased um in in
homes where their parents were are a
parent or sometimes two parents were
alcoholics. Um, definitely therapy is
needed cuz they need to unpack all of
that and deal with all of that that they
couldn't deal with um when they were
when they were young. So,
um, we have just a few more moments and
a little bit more time for questions.
Again, we're going to take a deeper dive
into this in two weeks when Dr. White
can be back with us. He had an urgent
call that he had to to take. Um but uh
we're going to look more at the disease
of alcoholism, what it does to the body
again, what it does to uh your
relationships and how you even how you
even get there sometimes how you even
get there to become an alcoholic. So,
we're going to look into this deeper.
Um, and even how like somebody asked how
you can help people. If you have um a
loved one that is an alcoholic or a
friend that is a alcoholic and you're
wanting to help them, what is the best
thing that you can do? So, we're going
to take a deeper deeper look into that.
But um yeah, so if you have any more
questions or comments, you can like I
said, there's just a few more minutes um
and then we're going to we're going to
close out for this evening. But before
we do, I'd like to put up Dr. White's um
program on stress that is free that uh
he will be doing um here. So I think
we're going to put that in the chat.
There it is. The Mastermind Institute.
Click on that. Um I'm not I don't
remember the dates. I want to say I
think the 13th which is Sunday the 13th
I think it's starting and it's free. Um
and so you're not going to want to miss
that. You're not going to want to miss
that. Let teaching us how to deal with
stress because it's always we all have
stress, right? We all have stress and we
need to learn how to deal with it in a
healthy way. Okay, Ashley, at this point
it's more like the dry alcoholic where
the substance isn't used, but the
walking on eggshells uh and triggers are
still present. Yeah.
So, in that situation,
um it's like they've stopped using
alcohol, but they haven't dealt with the
foundational issues that caused them to
start drinking in the first place. And
so now it's just like they're bitter and
angry and like because they're not
numbing themselves with the alcohol
anymore and they haven't dealt with the
foundational issue, they're still going
to be just a very moody, unpredictable
person. And so that's why you're still
walking on eggshells. So really stop to
stop drinking is great, but you but you
still this person still needs to deal
with the core foundational issues that
cause them to start drinking. Um because
they they need to heal and they need to
deal with with those things and and
until then they're pretty they're going
to be a pretty miserable unhappy person
until that
happens. So yeah. All right. Yes. Gloria
Alanon is a program for the family of
alcoholics. It is a great program.
Um so yeah, you guys can look that up.
That's another resource. It's a great
program. Okay. Well, um want to thank
you guys. Sorry that today was a little
it was shorter than normal. We had some
issues to get on. We got in late, but I
still think some really positive things
were shared even when Dr. White was on
here. And hopefully some of the things
that I've been able to share towards the
end were helpful as well. But we are
going to there's definitely a part two
to this uh a complete part two that will
happen in two weeks. So want you to be
back here with us. Bring a friend. Um
bring someone that you know that has
either had to uh has an alcoholic spouse
or been raised by an alcoholic or even
dealing has done dealt with some of
these things themselves. Um and just let
them know that this is the topic that we
are are talking about. Um, so we look
forward to seeing you in two weeks and
hope you have a good rest of the
evening. See you. See you soon.